<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title><![CDATA[Eating Horror]]></title>
	<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/"/>
	<updated>2014-09-01T14:22:11-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://eatinghorror.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Ben Augarten]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-09-01]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-09-01/"/>
		<updated>2014-09-01T14:16:34-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-09-01</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>kale</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>kale</li>
<li>sweet potato w/ coconut oil</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Lifestyle</h2>

<ul>
<li>Gym

<ul>
<li>95 squat</li>
<li>105 bench</li>
<li>65 row</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Up late night before

<ul>
<li>On call stuff w/ Stocktwits</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>None so far</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-31]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-31/"/>
		<updated>2014-09-01T14:14:15-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-31</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>pork chop</li>
<li>zucchini</li>
<li>kale</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>pork chop</li>
<li>zucchini</li>
<li>kale</li>
<li>sweet potato w/ coconut oil</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dinner

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>zucchini</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<p>Today I had some nice poops and generally felt quite good
* type 4, 7/10
* type 5, 6/10</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-30]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-30/"/>
		<updated>2014-09-01T14:13:12-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-30</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t remember exactly what I had
* Some combination of burgers, sauerkraut, broccoli, sweet potato</p>

<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>Type 5, 5/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-29]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-29/"/>
		<updated>2014-09-01T14:10:51-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/09/01/2014-08-29</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<p>Honestly, I do not remember what I ate today (I&rsquo;m writing this three days later)</p>

<p>I had some combination of pork chops, kale, and sweet potato</p>

<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>type 5-6, 4/10</li>
<li>type 5, 5/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-28]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/28/2014-08-28/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-28T20:06:20-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/28/2014-08-28</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>saurkraut</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>sweet potato</li>
<li>coconut oil</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dinner

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>kale</li>
<li>pork loin chop</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>type 6, 3/10</li>
<li>type 5, 4/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-27]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/28/2014-08-27/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-28T20:04:04-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/28/2014-08-27</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>roasted veggies</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>chuck steak</li>
<li>broccoli</li>
<li>roasted veggies</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dinner

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>sauerkraut</li>
<li>broccoli</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>type 6, 3/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-26]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/26/2014-08-26/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-26T19:31:27-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/26/2014-08-26</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>london broil</li>
<li>roasted parsnips, rutabaga, carrots, beets</li>
<li>baby bok choy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>chuck steak</li>
<li>baby bok choy</li>
<li>roasted parsnips, rutabaga, carrots, beets</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dinner

<ul>
<li>chuck steak</li>
<li>roasted parsnips, rutabaga, carrots, beets</li>
<li>wild, fresh salmon filet</li>
<li>organic liver &amp; sauteed yellow onion</li>
<li>peppermint tea</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<p>I went to the gym to find out my 5 rep maxes Monday. I ended up overstressing my body, since I&rsquo;ve been quite inactive for the last few weeks. I think it affected my symptoms for today.</p>

<ul>
<li>type 5, 5/10</li>
<li>type 5, 5/10</li>
<li>type 5, 4/10</li>
<li>type 5, 3/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-25]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/25/2014-08-25/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-25T21:15:08-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/25/2014-08-25</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>breakfast

<ul>
<li>london broil</li>
<li>baby bok choy roasted w/ EVOO</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lunch

<ul>
<li>burgers</li>
<li>&frac12; acorn squash (roasted w/ coconut oil)</li>
<li>sauteed kale</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>snack

<ul>
<li>roasted root veggies (parsnip, rutabaga, beets, carrots)</li>
<li>sweet potato w/ coconut oil</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Peppermint tea</li>
<li>dinner

<ul>
<li>london broil</li>
<li>baby bok choy roasted w/ EVOO</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<p>From now on, I&rsquo;ll simply rate using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_stool_scale">Bristol stool scale</a> as well as my more qualitative scale out of 10. This will help me make graphs and correlations with diet</p>

<ul>
<li>1 BM, type 5, 6/10</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-23]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-23/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:48:04-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-23</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>Steak</li>
<li>Grilled chicken + green juice</li>
<li>few pieces of pineapple and burgers</li>
<li>dried mango (2 servings, 40g sugar) @airport</li>
<li>ATE OUT &mdash; sausage and sauteed dino kale, beets (I got home from the airport after grocery stores had closed)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>No BMs, which was a nice relief</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-22]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-22/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:46:18-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-22</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>green juice</li>
<li>streak, burger, zucchini, &frac14; acorn squash (I was hungry)</li>
<li>steak, zucchini, squash</li>
<li>Apple chips with cinnamon (I was out very late and hadn&rsquo;t eaten in ~12 hours)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 BM, still diarrhea, discolored</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-20]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-20/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:39:41-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-20</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t keep track of food intake. It included a green juice, meat, and sweet potato. I stopped eating vegetables to see if that would help symptoms improve</p>

<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>~10 BMs</li>
<li>intermittent, severe intestinal pain</li>
<li>I could actually feel food move through my colon&hellip; a somewhat new and bizarre experience for me</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-21]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-21/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:39:03-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-21</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>steak and zucchini</li>
<li>more steak</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>down to 3 BMs! About the same quality though</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-19]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-19/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:34:47-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-19</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<p>I ate sparingly to try to avoid symptoms, but it did include</p>

<ul>
<li>roasted broccoli, chicken and sweet potato</li>
<li>steak w/ acorn squash</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>~15 BMs throughout the day, all of which were equally horrible</li>
<li>intermittent severe stomach pain, blinding at times</li>
</ul>


<h2>Extra</h2>

<p>Did blood work at the doctor today and got CBC results &mdash; I am not anemic! This result tells me that most of the damage was done more recently and for the most part my body has been absorbing important nutrients.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[2014-08-18]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-18/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:32:03-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/2014-08-18</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h2>Food</h2>

<ul>
<li>anesthetics for colonscopy</li>
<li>homemade chicken soup (chicken, parsnip, carrot, herbs)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Symptoms</h2>

<ul>
<li>probably ~10 throughout the day from the prep, all of which were equally horrible</li>
<li>intermittent stomach pain</li>
</ul>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Colonoscopy Day]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/colonoscopy-day/"/>
		<updated>2014-08-24T12:22:01-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/08/24/colonoscopy-day</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Results were less favorable than I wanted, but on par for what I expected. I had been cheating frequently in June and July and it seems the coffee and chocolate had caught up to me. I wasn&rsquo;t anticipating great results.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>Severe Swelling in rectum</li>
<li>Inflammation and moderate activity in the transverse colon</li>
<li>stricture in the ascending colon (old news, this is predominantly scar tissue and won&rsquo;t likely improve)</li>
</ul>


<p>My doctor recommended that I go back on Humira, but I decided to give myself 2-3 months of strict compliance, keep a journal, and use qualitative measurements as well as an MRI at the end of the time to reevaluate my situation and decide if medication is necessary.</p>

<p>Today marks the first day of my journey, treating severe Crohns without anti-inflammatories or immunosuppresants.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be publicly sharing all the foods that I eat and everything that leaves my body. You can follow that action on the <a href="http://eatinghorror.com/journal">journal</a> page of my blog. I&rsquo;ll also be giving larger updates on the home page.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Time Saving Tips]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/06/time-saving-tips/"/>
		<updated>2014-03-06T19:16:52-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/06/time-saving-tips</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Time is precious. We don&rsquo;t have time to carefully craft every dish, nor should we strive to. Yes, we should take pleasure in cooking and most importantly eating, but sometimes there is no time for that. The number one response I hear when I out myself as AIP is &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t have time to eat like that.&rdquo; I hear it from those with autoimmune diseases, coworkers, friends and family. Well &mdash; I&rsquo;m sorry, but you do have time to eat like me, and here&rsquo;s how.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Cook in bulk</h2>

<p>Ok, this one isn&rsquo;t a secret. I cook as if I were feeding a family of 5&hellip; always. If I&rsquo;m cooking something and it isn&rsquo;t going to feed me for at least 3 meals (some exceptions exist, I&rsquo;ll get to them), I won&rsquo;t cook it. I cannot possibly live my life if I have to cook more than once a day (I usually cook less than once a day). I tend to cook nights and then eat that for dinner, breakfast, lunch and possibly more if it lasts. I like to carve out at least 3 nights a week that I don&rsquo;t have to cook. I almost always have food in my fridge to eat so I can take these nights more flexibly. Having plentiful food also makes it orders of magnitude easier to stay compliant.</p>

<h2>Find a restaurant</h2>

<p>Yes, I am encouraging you to eat out. But &mdash; I want you to have a conversation with the restaurant. Where I live, there is a restaurant <a href="http://zealfood.com/">zeal</a> that serves a bowl with cauliflower rice, roasted veggies (nightshade free), and pasture raised beef. I went over all of the ingredients with them and feel completely comfortable eating there. Now, I don&rsquo;t go there all the time, but I do go about once a week to relax and feel normal. Additionally, it provides a nice backup in case I want to go out one night I don&rsquo;t have to worry about having enough food in the fridge &mdash; I can always just go to my preapproved restaurant.</p>

<h2>Cook meat and vegetables separately</h2>

<p>It might make meals less exciting, but cooking vegetables and meat separately is an enormous time saver. You can quickly sauté or roast veggies while slow cooking meat. Separately cooking them tends to result in less prep time because it forces you to make simpler meals. Additionally, now your vegetable supplies and meat supplies can vary independently &mdash; you can tune ratios, cook more of one without more of the other, and generally makes cooking faster and eating easier.</p>

<h2>Food is fuel</h2>

<p>Remember that food is merely the raw input to your body. Keeping this in mind can help change how you approach cooking and eating and help you prioritize other aspects of your life. It can be hard to remember that food doesn&rsquo;t have to be <em>amazing</em> while drooling over the AIP blogs. In times of need, taste can be sacrificed. When I&rsquo;m in a hurry, I don&rsquo;t brown meat before slow cooking it, or sauté minced veggies before throwing them into a meatloaf. It makes my life easier and I don&rsquo;t mind the taste. I call it functional eating.</p>

<h2>Throw away meals</h2>

<p>I have go to meals I make when I want to produce vast quantities of food in small chunks of time. I make meatloaf nearly every week (recipe pending). I can make 6 meals worth of food in about 20 minutes of prep time, 1 hour in the oven. I can throw a roast in the slow cooker in about 5 minutes. I can have broccoli roasted in 40 minutes, kale sautéed in 15, fish broiled in 12, liver and onions in 20. These are my quick meals &mdash; when I don&rsquo;t want to cook.</p>

<h2>Special Meals</h2>

<p>The above only works when you balance the equation with special meals. Meals that you go out of your way to make delicious &mdash; better than you or any of your friends have ever had. Special meals trick myself into cleaning my kitchen and remind myself that I really do enjoy cooking. Special meals remind myself that AIP is not restrictive and I can find pleasure in compliant foods. Special meals are what you find on blogs and in recipe books. My favorite is ginger garlic scallion crusted salmon (recipe pending). No one tells you how to make throw away meals though, so I will. Stay tuned.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Why AIP?]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/05/why-aip/"/>
		<updated>2014-03-05T20:46:05-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/05/why-aip</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>AIP, or Autoimmune Protocol, is a set of diet and lifestyle changes that help cure a leaky gut and reverse autoimmune disease. I&rsquo;m not going to bore you with cellular level details, but instead give you a general idea of the mechanics behind autoimmune diseases and AIP can help cure them. If you want the nitty gritty, scientific response to drop on your friends and family when they give you quizzical looks, please refer to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1936608391/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1936608391&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=eatihorr-20">The Paleo Approach</a> &mdash; it’s fun arguing with science on your side, trust me.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Now, before we talk any further I need to convince you that a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intestinal_permeability">leaky gut</a> is a necessary precursor to any autoimmune disease (and that without a leaky gut, autoimmune disease cannot happen). Luckily, scientists have begun researching exactly that. One group of scientists found that &ldquo;increased intestinal permeability&hellip; is observed prior to disease and appears to be involved in disease pathogenesis&rdquo;<sup>1</sup>. Another concluded that when the intercellular junctions are deregulated, autoimmune diseases can occur<sup>2</sup>. There is mounting evidence that leaky gut precedes all autoimmune diseases (there are still some autoimmune diseases for which this hasn’t been explicitly proven), and, more importantly, that autoimmune disease cannot happen if a leaky gut is not present. Therefore, helping our bodies fix our intestinal linings helps cure autoimmune disease<sup>3</sup>.</p>

<p>If you are still not convinced, I would suggest buying and reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1936608391/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1936608391&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=eatihorr-20">The Paleo Approach</a>. If you are still not convinced, I ask you to think for a second – do you really think that eating more whole foods, reducing sugar and high glycemic load foods, reducing preservatives, and increasing the nutrient density of your diet will not help your disease? I hope you intuitively believe that your body is capable of healing itself if given the opportunity.</p>

<p>There are several main ways we can help our bodies heal. We can reduce foods that irritate the gut or are hard to digest, increase foods that are nutrient dense and easier to digest, and reduce stress.</p>

<p>Now, there is an incredibly long list of foods that irritate the gut &mdash; don&rsquo;t be alarmed. Some of these foods you might be able to introduce back into your diet after disease stabilizes. This list includes eggs, nuts, seeds, nightshades, alcohol, <a href="http://www.thepaleomom.com/2013/03/gluten-cross-reactivity-update-how-your-body-can-still-think-youre-eating-gluten-even-after-giving-it-up.html">gluten cross-reactive foods</a>, excessive fructose, as well as grains, legumes, dairy, sugar, vegetable oils, or any processed foods/chemical/nitrates/etc. Minimizing these foods will give your body a much needed break from fighting itself to give it a chance for healing.</p>

<p>In order to heal, we want to give our body nutrient dense food. My personal favorite is beef liver. I literally feel happier just by eating beef liver. Usually, I eat liver (or other organ meats) about four times a week, or about 1lb every week. Some people don&rsquo;t like the taste and some will tell you to freeze it and take it like a pill. I disagree<sup>4</sup>. I used to dislike the taste of beef liver, I&rsquo;ll admit it, but it grew on me quickly. Now I look forward to my liver days, and often crave it on days that I don&rsquo;t get to eat any. The entire process of cooking and eating it brightens my day.</p>

<p>Another important food to include is fish and shellfish (for DHA and EPA omega 3&rsquo;s). Prefer wild, oily fish (even canned is ok), but don’t let anyone tell you that farmed fish isn’t ok as well for those on a budget. Then of course vegetables &mdash; green at every meal, colors elsewhere, eat the rainbow (not skittles). Buy vegetables you don’t know and google ways to make them delicious. We also want quality grass fed, pasture raised meats. Similarly, look for quality fats, coming from quality meats or use olive oil, coconut oil, or avocado oil. If grass fed or pasture raised meats are out of the question, favor leaner meats and supplement with health fats.</p>

<p>Stress reduction is probably the hardest to nail down and give general guidelines, which coincidentally makes it the hardest for those following the AIP protocol to really follow. I enjoy meditation and regular exercise to help manage my stress, and I always ensure I get at least 9 hours of sleep (sometimes I need more). Those with autoimmune disease tend to need more sleep than others. Feeling tired throughout the day is not normal &mdash; get more sleep. A lot of the difficult comes from the fact that we are often disconnected from ourselves. It is this section that we really need to check in with how we’re feeling, disconnect from the fast paced world and enjoy our lives – it is harder than it sounds.</p>

<p>I know this is a large list. I know this seems impossible. It isn&rsquo;t. My goal is to provide you with the tools necessary to transform your life and gain some sense of control over whatever plagues you.</p>

<p>I am 21 years old &mdash; I have followed the autoimmune protocol in college, while working full time, living in Vancouver and Italy, vacationing, and through personal crises. It is possible &mdash; <a href="https://twitter.com/EatingHorror">follow me</a> on twitter to find out.</p>

<p>(1) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1856434/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1856434/</a></p>

<p>(2) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22109896">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22109896</a></p>

<p>(3) I&rsquo;m being brief. If you&rsquo;re interested in the specifics, check out <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1936608391/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1936608391&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=eatihorr-20">The Paleo Approach</a></p>

<p>(4) I have no medical reason to disagree &mdash; you can feel free to pop frozen liver pills of that sounds good to you.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Fish Stock]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/04/fish-stock/"/>
		<updated>2014-03-04T18:31:48-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/04/fish-stock</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Apparently Whole Foods just gives fish heads away! That means I&rsquo;m making stock tonight. Here&rsquo;s how:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is extraordinarily easy to make and very healthy. Fish provide iodine &mdash; an important nutrient that other foods permitted on the autoimmune protocol lack, making fish stock an essential staple. Iodine is an important element in regulating thyroid activity. Fish stock also provides all of the same benefits that beef stock provides.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to use my 6-quart <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004P2NG0K/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B004P2NG0K&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=eatihorr-20">slow cooker</a> to do most of the heavy lifting. Before we get started, you&rsquo;ll need</p>

<ul>
<li>2 fish heads and/or carcasses (I used only one fish head and it turned out OK, but two would be twice as good)</li>
<li>1 onion, chopped</li>
<li>3-4 carrots, chopped</li>
<li>acid (lemon, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001I7MVG0/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B001I7MVG0&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=eatihorr-20">ACV</a>, or other)</li>
<li>filtered water, enough to cover</li>
<li>salt</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, all you have to do it throw everything into your favorite slow cooker and turn it on low.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/1Z1BQmy.jpg" alt="My fish stock pre cook" /></p>

<p>After about 6-7 hours, you will have extracted all of the fishy goodness. Next, pour the stock through a fine strainer or sieve into containers for storage. I suggest refrigerating some and freezing some for later. About 1 cup per day is plenty if you&rsquo;re trying to maintain health, or 2 cups a day is recommended if you&rsquo;re currently in a flare or otherwise need to give your body some extra help.</p>

<p>Happy fishing!</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Eating Horror?]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/03/why-eating-horror/"/>
		<updated>2014-03-03T19:55:42-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://eatinghorror.com/blog/2014/03/03/why-eating-horror</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Partly as a homage to <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com">codinghorror</a> &mdash; I&rsquo;m a developer by day &mdash; but mostly because I now look back on my old eating habits with horror. I want to help others make that same realization. I want everyone to feel empowered to take control of their health. Let me back up.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In August of 2006 I was diagnosed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ankylosing_spondylitis">ankylosing spondylitis</a> (arthritis). The doctors initially thought I broke my toe until my other foot ballooned days later. In 2008, I developed psoriosis, a minor annoyance. In January of 2013 I was diagnosed with Crohns Disease (CD). I was actually diagnosed with severe CD &mdash; I had a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fistula">fistula</a> in my colon and a <a href="http://www.crohnsforum.com/wiki/Stricture">stricture</a> &mdash; severe enough for me to go on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mesalazine">mesalamin</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humira">Humira</a> (you may have seen it on TV). That&rsquo;s three autoimmune diseases before the age of 21.</p>

<p>Since then, I have taken to an elimination diet (AIP paleo) popularized by <a href="http://www.thepaleomom.com/">Paleo Mom</a>, and I haven&rsquo;t looked back since &mdash; well, only a few times. It is nearly one year later and I can say that all of my diseases are improved and I am gearing up to go off of my medication.</p>

<p>This blog is only tangentially about me though &mdash; mostly how my experiences can help you and draw connections between your experiences and mine. Really, the goal of this blog is to find and give support for those trying to give their bodies the necessary materials to heal themselves au natural. I hope to provide tips and strategies to help people be compliant in their day to day lives, help them regain control when we cheat (it&rsquo;s inevitable), and motivate. I strongly suggest subscribing to <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/AutoImmuneProtocol/">/r/AutoimmuneProtocol</a>, or <a href="https://twitter.com/EatingHorror">following me</a> on twitter</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>
